<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints expectation and reward a sermon at the funerall of that learned and faithfull minister of Christ Mr. Tho: Wiborow June 10th 1652. / Preached at Enfeild in Staffordshire, by Michael Thomas minister of Gods word at Stockden in Shropshire.</title>
            <author>Thomas, Michael, rector of Stockton.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E835_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207408</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866461</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 127:E835[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints expectation and reward a sermon at the funerall of that learned and faithfull minister of Christ Mr. Tho: Wiborow June 10th 1652. / Preached at Enfeild in Staffordshire, by Michael Thomas minister of Gods word at Stockden in Shropshire.</title>
                  <author>Thomas, Michael, rector of Stockton.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Princis Armes in St Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Peter, 2nd III, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS EXPECTATION AND REWARD A SERMON AT THE FUNERALL of that Learned and Faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt Mr. <hi>THO: WIBOROW June</hi> 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1652.</p>
            <p>Preached at <hi>Enfeild</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> By <hi>MICHAEL THOMAS</hi> Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Stockden</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Marke the perfect Man, and behold the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, for the end of that man is Peace. <bibl>Pſal. 37. 37.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>The Righteous ſhall be had in everlaſting Remembrance. <bibl>Pſal. 112. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Bleſſed are the Dead that Dye in the Lord. <bibl>Revel. 14. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Princis Armes</hi> in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:168137:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168137:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2 Epiſt. Pet. 3d. chap. ver. 13.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Nevertheleſs we according to his promiſe look for new Heavens and a new Earth, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſs:</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt word of this Text invites us to look back to ſomewhat that went before, at the third Verſe, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle gives a propheticall caveat concerning a ſort of ſcoffers that ſhould come in the laſt daies, mockers at Religion, not onely bending all their wit and learning to diſpute againſt it, but deciding thoſe that ſpake of the comming of the Lord. <hi>Where is the promiſe of his comming,</hi> ſay they, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. 'twas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaies <hi>Aretius,</hi> a mocking, and ſcoffing queſtion, which argued not onely the proud wickedneſſe, but the deep ſecurity of their hearts. Now againſt theſe Saint <hi>Peter</hi> bends his main forces, and in this Epiſtle ſtirres up his diſperſed Countrymen the Jews, to ſtick cloſe to that Doctrine which was delivered by the Prophets and Apoſtles. For aſſure your ſelves (ſaith he) that as this VVorld had a beginning and once periſhed, ſo hereafter it ſhall have an end, and whatſoever theſe ſcoffers think, be conſumed with fire. <hi>Verſes</hi> 6, and 7. Neither think yee this time long a comming, for though it ſeem ſo to us, it is otherwiſe with God. <hi>Deo nihil eſt aut prius aut poſterius,</hi> ſay the Schoolmen, Gods actions are not meaſured by the rule of time, thoſe things which are paſt and future are preſent to him, <hi>for one day is as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day</hi> ver. 8. 'Tis the patience and long-ſuffering of the Lord which doth as it were ſet back the clock of time, that we might take the advantage of the means, and opportunities of grace, to repent and be provided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that day commeth: For come it ſhall, and that ſuddenly, <hi>as a thief in the night,</hi> ver. 9. and appear it ſhall, and that terribly, <hi>when the Heavens ſhall paſſe away with a great noiſe, and the Elements ſhall melt with fervent heat:</hi> verſe 10 but howſoever this univerſall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion ſhall ruine the frame of this world, and involve thoſe deſperate wretches in it, that reſt their hearts upon it; yet to us who have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the pretious faith through the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, it ſhall not occaſion the leaſt trouble; let the foundations of the Earth ſink away under our feet, let our habitations totter about our ears, let the air fail our noſtrills, or the Heavens to give us light. Nevertheleſſe we according to his promiſe look for new Heavens. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Text in the generall purpoſe, and deſign of it, preſents to us
<pb facs="tcp:168137:3"/>
this obſervation. That a righteous man hath both helps and hopes to depend upon, when the whole world failes him. A Doctrine very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and neceſſary to be diſcuſſed in theſe ſad times, we ſee by ſad and daily experiences, that the tenure of our Earthly poſleſſions is fickle and uncertain, thoſe Tabernacles of our fleſh wherein our ſoules dwell are continually decaying and mouldring away, and therefore the ſpirits of holy men had need to be ſupported with their future hopes, by the conſideration of thoſe glorious Manſions that are prepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Heaven for them. And when I have diſcuſſed this generall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, I proceed to ſpeak of theſe five particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, that the Eſtate of a Chriſtian in this life is an inheritance: 'tis not in poſſeſſion but in reverſion. <hi>Expectamus: wee look for.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſecond is, that this inheritance will certainly devolve and fall to him for his Evidence, for it is Gods promiſe: <hi>Wee according to his promiſe look for.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The third is the ſubſtance of the inheritance. <hi>Heaven and Earth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The forth is the quality of the inheritance. <hi>New Heavens and a new Earth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The fift is the excellence of the inheritance, <hi>wherein dwelleth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall guide your Chriſtian attention through theſe particulars, and collect thence ſuch notes of as may be proper to our ſelves, and ſutable to this preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>I begin with the generall obſervation. That a righteous man hath both helps and hopes to depend when the whole world failes him.</p>
            <p>'Twas a bleſſed Metaphor which the Holy Ghoſt put into the mouth of St. <hi>Paul, Pondus gloriae:</hi> When he ſaid that our afflictions are but light, becauſe there is an exceeding and an eternall weight of glory attending on them, for were it not for that exceeding weight of glory, no other weight in the world were able to turn the ſcale, or weigh down thoſe infinite weights of affliction which oppoſe us here; we read in the book of <hi>Exodus</hi> that God ſent upon <hi>Pharaoh peſtem valde gravem,</hi> a very heavy peſtilence, 9. 3d. in the eighth chap. <hi>Muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am valde gravem.</hi> God called in but the fly to vex the Egyptians, and even that flye was an heavy burthen to them. The diſtreſſed Church of the Jews complain'd <hi>Lament.</hi> 3. that God <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravaſſet compedes,</hi> had made their fetters and their chains heavy to them, and the workmen in the harveſt. <hi>Math.</hi> 20. complain that they had born the heat &amp; burthen of the day. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> both cryed out and ſaid, that this work is vanity and lightneſſe when wee ſee all is weight and burden, and heavineſſe and oppreſſion; what man that lives may not ſay, and that truly, trouble and heavineſſe are
<pb facs="tcp:168137:3"/>
fallen upon me, ſo that were there not a weight of future glory to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſe it, we ſhould all ſink into nothing.</p>
            <p>And that which multiplies the ſadneſſe of this conſideration, is, that ſtill the beſt men have the moſt heavy afflictions laid upon them. No ſooner do we hear God ſay of <hi>Job</hi> that he had found a juſt man, one that fear'd God and eſchewed evill, but immediately God grants a Commiſſion to Satan to bring in the Sabeans and Chaldeans upon his ſervants and cattle, fire and tempeſt upon his children, and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom diſeaſes upon his body. Although God gave that teſtimony of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David,</hi> hat he was a man according to his own heart; yet we may read ſeveral croſſes that befel him in the miſcarriages &amp; diſobediences of his Children. Yea, our bleſſed Saviour himſelf, of whom God teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at his baptiſm, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> Yet we find that beloved Son led up by the ſpirit to be tempted in the Wilderneſſe. <hi>Math.</hi> 4. Afterward you may hear God ratifying the ſame teſtimony at his transfiguration. <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> and yet find that Son forſaken of his Father, and given over to Scribes and Phariſees, and Publicans and Herodians, and Prieſts and Souldiers, and People and Judges, and Witneſſes, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioners, and he that was called the beloved Son of God, and made partaker of the glory of Heaven in this world, in his transfiguration, was made the ſink of all corruption, the receptacle of the pollution of all the ſins of the world, as if he were no Son of God, but meer man; as if he were no man but a contemptible worm: ſuch is the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition of mankind: As though the greateſt weakneſſe in the world were man, and the greateſt fault in man were to be good. Man is more miſerable then any other Creature, and good men more miſerable then any other men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of a ſore evill that was under the Sun, and this was it, that all things come alike to all, that there is but one event to the righteous and to the wicked; in times of common and publique ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitity when God plats an overflowing ſcourge for a Nation, tis of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſeen that ſome ſtripes doe light upon the backs of the righteous: Good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> ſlain in the warrs, aſwell as wicked <hi>Ahab;</hi> and this is an evill of vexation, becauſe ſometimes weak Chriſtians are offended that it is ſo, and the glory of God ſeems to be obſcured, when it is ſo; but yet God, who beſt knowes how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair his own honour, ſuffers and appoints it ſo, that the juſt and the unjuſt are wrapped up in the ſame judgment together. The Corn you know is as much beaten in the thraſhing as the chaffe, or the ſtraw is: and the juſt are as much chaſtned in this world as the unjuſt; of which proceedings of God, <hi>Aquinas</hi> gives this account, <hi>All things,</hi> ſaith he,
<pb facs="tcp:168137:4"/>
               <hi>happen alike to all, quantum ad ſubſtantiam bonorum &amp; malorum, ſed non quantum ad finem:</hi> In regard of the ſubſtance of good and evill, ſo all things happen alike; but not in reſpect of their end; becauſe righteous men by theſe viſitations are humbled, and brought into the way of bleſſedneſſe, whereas by them wicked men are hardned, and go on more ſtubbornly in the waies of their iniquitie. Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in ſending out theſe meſſengers of wrath, is, but to declare his indignation againſt ſinne; and when his children perceive that ſin is ſo odious and contrary to his nature, they grow by degrees into the ſame hatred and deteſtation of it: and then it is that the Lord takes them into his eſpeciall protection, and will be their help and comfort when the whole world failes them.</p>
            <p>And this was that priviledge which the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſang ſo triumphantly, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 91. <hi>Who ſo dwelleth under the defence of the moſt high, ſhall abide under the ſhadow of the Almightie.</hi> The Argument of that Pſalm, ſaies <hi>Muſculus,</hi> is the confidence and affiance of a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſoul upon God; the particulars of every confidence, holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> deſcribes from the firſt to the fourteenth verſe; under theſe meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoricall tearms, of a ſecret place and a ſhadow, are ſet forth the care and providence of God: as if <hi>David</hi> had ſaid, 'tis true, that troubles will befall the people of God, but God hath a ſecret place to ſecure them; the fire of tribulation may be kindled round about them, but God hath a ſhadow to refreſh them, be the judgment of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſoever, God hath ſuitable deliverances for his people: are they in poverty or nakedneſſe? the Lord will cover them with his feathers; are they ſick and ſore at heart? he hath healing under his wings; are they purſued with the ſword? the Lord will be their buckler; are they affraid of the peſtilence? that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the LXX read it, that evill Angell, that deſtroyes evening, and morning, and at noon day, yet it ſhall not come nigh his dwelling; thouſands ſhall fall upon his right hand, and ten thouſand upon his left, but the Lord ſhall give his Angels charge over him, to keep him in all his waies. And all theſe deliverances <hi>David</hi> found in himſelf, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that God faſhion'd him in his Mothers womb, and took him thence, and was both his hope and his help afterward, he did often break the ſnare of the hunter, defeating the malice of <hi>Saul</hi> and the rebellion of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and carried him through divers tribulations, and at length laid him in his grave, full of daies, riches, and honour. The holy Scripture abounds with examples of this kind, that God hath been a ſhield and buckler to his people, and hath ſatisfied them with long life and ſalvation, that have put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>And for the great comfort and encouragement of his people, the
<pb facs="tcp:168137:4"/>
Lord hath told them, that he will be a father unto them, ſee <hi>Pſalm 103. Like as a father pittieth his children, ſo will the Lord pittie them that fear him.</hi> See <hi>Malach. 3. 16. They ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord, in that day when I make up my jewells. In that day,</hi> That is, in the day of trouble and deſolation, when the Lord ſhall put a difference between the righteous and the wicked, in that day they ſhall be mine, and that love and favour which a tender Father ſheweth to an obedient ſon, ſo will ſpare them. Why? they are my Jewels, ſaith God, my pretious Treaſure, &amp; though like Jewells, they may have flawes &amp; faults in them, and yield not that brightneſſe and luſtre they ſhould do, yet I will cut them, and poliſh them, and lay them up in the Cabinet of the grave, and bring them out on the glorious day of reſnrrection: but becauſe of the two parents, for the moſt part, the love of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is moſt tender; therefore it hath pleaſed God to aſcertain his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his tender care over them, even in that notion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 15, 16. <hi>Can a Mother forget her ſucking child, and not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb? If ſhe could, yet I will not forget thee.</hi> But what is there provided to keep them in Gods remembrance; <hi>I have graven thee upon the Palmes of my Hands,</hi> ſaies the Lord there: That phraſe, ſaies <hi>Alvarez,</hi> imports <hi>perpetuam recordationem,</hi> a conſtant remembrance, never to be blotted out; as we uſe to ſay of a thing that is nigh, and neer to us, <hi>pro manibus eſt, it is at hard:</hi> But there is more in that phraſe then ſo; there are ſome Divines conceive, that our Saviour now in the ſtate of glory, retaines the ſcares and wounds which he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his bodie here on earth for the redemption of mankind. 'Twas the ſaying of Saint <hi>Cyprian, The Lord Chriſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the print of the nails in his hands and feet, that the offering up of his bodie for a ſacr fice, might every day be as powerfull in the ſight of God, to appeaſe his wrath towards mankind, as it was on the day of his paſſion. Oſtendit filius patri vulnera,</hi> ſaies <hi>Aquinas, Chriſt ſhews his wounds to his father, and they are as ſo many wounds pleading and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for penitent ſinners.</hi> So that theſe words, <hi>that God will remember his people more tenderly, then a mother can her child,</hi> that the names of his Elect are written in the palmes of his hands in ſuch bloody characters, that no time can deface: how ſtrong an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may this be to every Chriſtian, that Chriſt will be a friend, and ſtick to him when the whole world ſhall fail him?</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerving thoſe many names and relations, by which the Lord is pleaſed to own his people, breaks forth into this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, <hi>Omnia Chriſtus eſt nobis, Chriſt is all in all to us.</hi> Is thy conſcience wounded, Chriſt is a Phyſician; are thy ſins many and grievous? Chriſt is righteouſneſſe; doſt thou walk in darkneſſer
<pb facs="tcp:168137:5"/>
Chriſt is light; wouldſt thou go to heaven? he is the way; doſt thou fear death? Chriſt is the life. <hi>Vide quot titulorum generibus tui gratia Chriſtus inſignitur,</hi> ſaies that father: See how many names and titles Chriſt takes upon him for thy ſake, who in his own Eſſence is but one God, that in all the changes and chances that may befall us in this life, we may have ſome name and notion of God to lay hold upon, and to ſuſtain us in the day of adverſity.</p>
            <p>But ſome carnal heart perchance may ſay, if the Lord be the help &amp; the hope of his people, how is it that they are oftentimes brought into ſuch ſtraits, that they know not which way to turn themſelvs; we might ſatisfie this and the like objections, if we would but conſider of theſe things: Firſt, it is very meet that every child ſhould honour his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that every ſervant ſhould glorifie his Maſter: In the afflictions of his holy ones, the Lord lets the wicked ſee, how much they will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his ſake, and not forſake him, that they will not leave their integritie, though they loſe all the world beſide. <hi>Doſt thou ſtill retain thine integritie,</hi> ſaies <hi>Jobs</hi> wife to him? Doſt thou fear ſuch a God as hath ſtripped thee of all thy earthly comforts? Oh, ſaies <hi>Job, ſhall we receive good from the hand of the Lord, and ſhall we not receive evil? The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> Again, it is not meet that children and ſervants ſhould receive correction from their Parents and Maſters to remember them of, and to obtain them in their duty. <hi>Secundi ſucceſſus abducunt a Deo &amp; ſanctimonia,</hi> ſaies <hi>Hyperius;</hi> proſperitie and happineſſe do eſtrange or hearts from Godlineſſe, and ſlacken us in all duties of devotion. this corruption, <hi>David</hi> acknowledged in his own nature, <hi>Man being honour, hath no underſtanding:</hi> And further, <hi>Before I was afflicted I went wrong, but now I will keep thy teſtimonies:</hi> The Vine will grow empty and wild except it be pruned, and ſo will the beſt man except the Lord ſomtime ſhake his rod over him. <hi>Iraſcitur Divina Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas in hoc ſoeculo ne iraſcatur in altero.</hi> Almighty God will be angry with us in this world, that he may favour us in the next, and in mercy corrects us here, that he may not conſume us in vengeance hereafter.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, It is not meet that every one ſhould wear the badge and cognizance of his profeſſion. <hi>Luther</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>Qui non eſt crucianus, non eſt Chriſtianus:</hi> He that is not crucified to the world, &amp; the world to him, is no Chriſtian and ſome ſtories tell us, that the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians had an Hieroglyphick, <hi>Crucem coronatam,</hi> a Croſs with a Crown upon it, &amp; it had this inſcription. <hi>Tolle crucem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere coronam,</hi> you muſt bear the Croſs if ye would wear the Crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if we be the members of Chriſt, we muſt conform to our head, &amp; partake with our fellow members, wee muſt not expect that God ſhould ſtrew
<pb facs="tcp:168137:5"/>
carpets for our nice feet to walk into Heaven, and make that way ſmooth for us, which all the Patriarchs and Prophets, and Apoſtles, and Martyrs, yea and Chriſt himſelfe found ſo rugged and bloody; the gate of Heaven is ſtreight, and we muſt ſtrive to enter into it, we muſt be diſpoſed and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in mind, cherfully to part with any thing we enjoy, when it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to call for it; <hi>This is the race we muſt run, this is the courſe we muſt finiſh,</hi> and yet we may not ſay within our ſelves, this is an hard ſaying; are theſe the helpes and hopes that a righteous man hath to depend upon whent he world failes him; ſurely wee miſtake our ſelves if we look for any other, for the eſtate of a Chriſtian is an inheritance, his happineſſe is not in poſſeſſion but in reverſion, which is the firſt of thoſe particulars I propounnded to conſider when I had handled the generall obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Expectamus</hi> ſaies the Apoſtle, there are ſome better things we look for then we poſſeſſe here. I am perſwaded a great part of that trouble that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls the children of God in this life ariſeth from a miſtake, becauſe our Saviour ſaies, <hi>that the meek ſhall inherit the Earth:</hi> therefore when meek and holy perſons are driven from their houſe and home, when their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſſions are taken from them by violence, hereupon they are caſt down and troubled, as if they were at once oppreſſed by men and forſaken of God: but this I ſay is a miſtake. Righteous men look upon the world as if it were their own, when they have a good title to it, yet they have the leaſt ſhare in it: the wealth of a Chriſtian is not in poſſeſſion: 'tis true what <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaies, <hi>Wiſdom is good with an inheritance;</hi> that man that is <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> too: He to whom God hath given both riches and religion, wealth and grace to manage it, goodly and fair is that mans lot God hath done ſo to ſome, but hee doth not promiſe to do ſo to all, when the Sons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> were preſented by their mother to our Saviours fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſit one on his right hand, the other on his left in his Kingdom, they received no other anſwer but this, <hi>can ye drink of my Cup,</hi> that is, <hi>can ye ſuffer with me? can ye powre out your blood for the profeſſion of my Goſpel:</hi> The Crown of of Martyrdom was all the honour which our Saviour offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to thoſe ambitious Diſciples. Our Saviour told <hi>Pilate</hi> that his Kingdom was not of this world, our eſtates then lie not on this old earth, but in thoſe new Heavens that we look for Neither do we find in Scripture that the Saints held by any other tenure: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies of <hi>Abraham, that he did but ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ourn in</hi> Canaan <hi>as in a ſtrange Country: he and his Children dwelling in Tents, for he looked for a City that had foundations, whoſe builder and maker was God:</hi> So <hi>Jacob</hi> deſcribes his own life, and calls it but a Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage. <hi>So David</hi> confeſſes that he was but a ſtranger and ſojourner as all his Fathers were: from whence proceeded theſe humble acknowledgements of theſe holy men but from this conſideration, that their eſtates were an i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>heritance, which as yet they were not in poſſeſſion of, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> aſſure themſelves of the reverſion; and this note may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:168137:6"/>
Firſt, if the Lord have given us wealth or other accomodations, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments in preſent poſſeſſion, it ſhould move us to thankfulneſſe How much are thoſe men bound to God, to whom he hath given the Earth in poſſeſſion, and Heaven in reverſion? how ſhould they endeavour to honour the Lord with their ſubſtance, who hath obliged them by ſo many mercies? And ſecondly, patience and contentedneſſe are vertues that are required of thoſe that are poor in this world; that man is too covetous that will not be ſatisfied unleſſe he have Earth and Heaven too. Let us conſider our ſelves, that while we are in this world we are heirs indeed, but in our nonage, we have a title to any good thing this world hath or the next but God who is our Guardian hath it in his hands, and allowes onely ſomething for our preſent maintenance, but when the few and evill daies of our pilgrimage be expired, then we ſhall poſſeſſe a City that hath foundations, which is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed and prepared for us, and which ſhall extreamly be eſtated on us, for the evidence wee have to ſhew for it is Gods promiſe, which is the ſecond particular we are to conſider. We according to his promiſe look for new Heavens and a new Earth.</p>
            <p>Man hath divers waies and meanes of apprehending things, that which we apprehend by ſenſe we call our knowledge, that which we know by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we call our reaſon, that which we know by tryal is our experience, but that which we receive for the authority of him that delivers it is, called faith. God hath promiſed eternall life to all them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, of this the authority of the word of God informs me, and my faith pitches upon it and there it reſts. It was well ſaid by <hi>Theophylact. Orationis fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum &amp; baſis eſt Fides. Fidei vero Dei promiſſio.</hi> The foundation of prayer is faith, for without faith prayer is ineffectuall: but the foundation of our faith are the promiſes of God in Chriſt Jeſus, and God was pleaſed to take that way of aſſurance for the comfort and ſupport of his people. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>God being willing to ſhew to the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs of his promiſe the immutability of his counſell, confirm'd it with an Oath.</hi> Onely for this reaſon that we might have ſtrong conſolation, ſuch a conſolation as will be a Tower and Fortreſſe of defence: ſuch a ſupport as will hold up our heads amidſt the raging floods, either of worldly afflictions or Satans tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; <hi>For all the promiſes of God are Yea and Amen in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> whatſoever the Lord promiſes ſhall certainly come to paſſe; <hi>Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but his word ſhall not paſſe away.</hi> And therefore if we would adviſe ſoundly for the good of our ſoules, we ſhould endeavour to be familiarly and intimately acquainted with the promiſes of God. 'Tis reported of one of the Rabbins <hi>Saadiah,</hi> that he could tell how often every letter in the Hebrew Alphabet was uſed in the whole Bible, and ſuch know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge argued great ſtudy and meditation in the Scripture. The troubles of a Chriſtian heart are very many, both for number, variety, and bitterneſſe, and there is onely one ingredient that can ſweeten them all, and that is the
<pb facs="tcp:168137:6"/>
promiſes of God. Can we remember what the Lord promiſes, <hi>that the ſeed of the righteous ſhall be bleſſed:</hi> that <hi>the Lord in his holy habitation will be a Father to the Fatherleſſe, and a Judge of the Widow: to ſet thoſe that are ſolitarie in families,</hi> as it is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 5. There is marrow in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſufficient to ſtrengthen every Chriſtian heart, that doth diſgeſt it by faith: can we remember it, and not be comforted? or who that conſiders thoſe words of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians, That the Lord is able to doe exceeding abundantly above all that we can ask or think.</hi> Eph. 3. 20. Heres a large patent for comfort, when trouble and anguiſh comes upon us, when all our affairs for this life are in a deſperate and forlorn condition, when matters go ſo ill with us, that we know not which way to turn our ſelves: if then the Lord ſhould put us to our choice, and bid us bethink our ſelves, and ask for thoſe things which we conceived would be moſt comfortable to us; yet the Lord is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we can ask or think: the Lord is not only better able to provide, but he knowes what is better for us then we our ſelves, and willl in due time adminiſter it abundantly to all thoſe, that caſt their care, and rely upon him. He is the Lord faithfull and true, that keepeth covenant and mercy with the righteous, and their ſeed, and that never turnes his face from them whoſe eyes are towards him. Foraſmuch then as the Lord hath paſſed his promiſe for all things, both of this life, and that which is to come, let us treaſure up in our memories a plenteous ſtore of theſe preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes, that in all the troubles and diſquiet of our hearts, we may have a cordiall ready to revive our fainting ſpirits: What though we be harrowed with oppreſſions, and rack'd with perſecutions? What though our eſtates be taken from us; nay, ſuppoſe the fire were kindled that muſt diſſolve the world, or death ready to diſſolve us, yet what can diſcourage us if we believe this promiſe, that a new heaven, and a new earth are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for us, and ſhall everlaſtingly abide with us, which is the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and calls for your Chriſtian attention.</p>
            <p>But I foreſee neither the time nor your patience will admit to conſider theſe particular branches of the Text apart, we are yet to ſpeak of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and the qualitie, and the excellencie of the inheritance of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, but of theſe, much need not, neither indeed can be ſaid: I know that ſome interpreters have made this text the foundation of that queſtion, whether after the generall diſſolution of theſe heavens and elements by fire, there ſhall reſult new heavens and a new earth out of the aſhes of the old world: there are great Authors on both ſides, and 'tis not for me to put in my head among the wiſe, as the proverb is, being mindfull of what <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſpeaks in this queſtion, <hi>In re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m dub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a nil pertin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter eſt aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dum: In ſuch a doubtfull caſe, we muſt not determine ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly:</hi> It may be ſufficient for us to know, that in theſe new heavens and earth there is that
<pb facs="tcp:168137:7"/>
joy and bliſſe, which no tongue can expreſſe, nor heart imagine, 'tis the buſineſſe only of our faith to believe that great goodneſs of the Lord that we ſhall ſee in the land of the living. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> tells us 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>That our inheritance in heaven is incorruptible, &amp; undefiled, and ſuch an one as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not fade away. Pareus</hi> gives us a criticiſme upon the place: that terme in the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we read incorruptible, he conceives ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, indiminiſhable which tearme would much advance our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inheritance; we obſerve of earthly inheritances, how great ſoever they be, they do not wholly deſcend upon the heir; the more children their are in a familie, into the more portions muſt the inheritance be divided, and every diviſion is a diminution: But this inheritance which Chriſt hath purchaſed for us, is given whole and entire to every ſon of God. <hi>Tanta eſt ſingulis, quanta eſt omnibus,</hi> ſaies Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> every bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoul enjoyes the whole heaven, and all the comforts of it, which are the rather enlarged, by the multitude of thoſe that partake of them. And again, it is ſuch an inheritance, wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe. 'Tis a nice, but a profitable note, that both <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrarius</hi> make, conceiving the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to referre rather to the perſons then the place, they render it thus: <hi>We in whom dwelleth the righteouſneſſe of faith, look for new heavens and a new earth:</hi> And admitting of this tranſlation, it may rouſe our ſouls and conſciences to conſider, whether true and ſaving righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe dwell in us or no, for 'tis that only that muſt give us title to that inheritance. Saint <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> tells us, that there ſhall in no wiſe enter into the new <hi>Jeruſalem, anything that defileth, or worketh abhomination, or marketh alie.</hi> Holy perſons we muſt be, as we hope to aſcend into the holy hill of the Lord. Or conſider the words as we read them, that righteouſneſſe referres to the place, and even that will exaſt the excellencie of it: Here in this world, righteouſneſſe doth but ſojurne, there it dwells; here it hath but a Tabernacle, there a Manſion; here it is mixed with manifold infirmities, there it is perfect, and in the greateſt eminency; here but in ſome, there in all; here but for a time, but there for ever: The unrighteonſneſſe of this preſent evill world, makes all thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to heaven to deſire to be diſſolved: Theſe are thoſe daies in which we may take up that crie of <hi>David, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lp Lord, for the godly man ceaſeth, and the faithfull fail from among the Children of men; they ſpeak with vain tongues, and ſlattering lipps, and double hearts, and are full of all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe:</hi> So that we may ſay, <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord,</hi> they do not only <hi>reſt from their labours,</hi> but are ſecured from all violence and unrighteouſneſſe, they neither know nor feel the evills that are done upon earth. Into which bleſſed ſtate, our confidence is, the ſoul of our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here diſceaſed is tranſlated, in the honour of whoſe memory I muſt yet begg a few minutes, to ſhew you in how many reſpects he was an example
<pb facs="tcp:168137:7"/>
of the Text, and both in life and death, a very eminent practiſer of it.</p>
            <p>I remember what <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaid of <hi>Antoninus, Pictores pulchram abſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamg, faciem raro niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us effingunt: An exact and comely face is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me drawn, but with ſome diſſadvantage.</hi> Perſons of great parts and gifts cannot with ſufficient right and juſtice be repreſented by one of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner abilities: I may ſay of him, what <hi>Nacianzen</hi> ſaid of Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>here wants his own tongue, to ſpeak his own ſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> that elegant and pious tongne, which you have ſo often heard reſounding the praiſes of God in this place. Yet ſince <hi>David</hi> tells us, that there is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour due to all the Saints of God, to ſuch as live and die in his holy faith; and ſince Providence put me upon the work (for I ſought it not) as I loved and honoured him living, it is ſome addition to my ſorrow for his death, that I cannot diſcharge this funerall rite in a meaſure anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his juſt deſert: In that great varietie of graces which ſhined emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently in him, I cannot tell which to ſelect and preſent firſt. It was the Fate of this reverend perſon to live in ſuch times, wherein this Prophecie of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in this Chapter, was over-abundantly fulfilled: He fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, that <hi>there ſhould be ſcoffers and jeſters in divine things,</hi> in matters appertaining to God and religion: For now in theſe daies, excellency of wit, lies in prophanneſſe, and he is reputed a good ſpirit that dares abuſe God and holy things; that perſon is eſteemed good company, who by his ſcurrile wit, makes his company the worſe, or keeps them from good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: This being the air and complexion of the wit of theſe times, I have been both an eye and ear witneſſe, that prophane wit hath oftentimes been a matter of vexation to him, but never of mirth that I could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. It pleaſed God to carry him through various fortunes, and yet to ſupport him with cheerfulneſſe, and a true Chriſtian conſtancie in all. It was an inverterate diſeaſe, no calamitie of theſe times, that occaſion'd his death: He hath given many teſtimonies of his firm faith in the Doctrine of our Text, that a righteous man hath both helps &amp; hopes to depend upon, when the world failes him; He ſaw, and had experience of many failings in the world, and worldly things: His eſtate failed him, which in the beginning of theſe troubles was full and plentifull: His friends failed him, and proved unfaithfull: His health and ſtrength failed him, and let his bodie fall into his grave like ripe fruit from a tree: and in all theſe defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencies and faultrings of the world, he bore up a true Chriſtian head, glorifying God in great patienee and integritie, ſubmitting to his holy will, aſwell in his loſſes as in his gaines, bleſſing God, both when he gave, and when he took away: He made the only right uſe of all his afflictions, by conſidering that they were ſent to teach him holy obedience, to fear God and to eſchew evill, in which important leſſons, he was ſo good a proficient, that like a dutifull ſervant, he had learnt to carry the Croſſe
<pb facs="tcp:168137:8"/>
of his Maſter Chriſt Jeſus after him. Thoſe ſtaunch and reſerved affections which he had to earthly things, did abundantly teſtifie that he placed his wealth and treaſure in his reverſions in heaven, not in any thing that he did, or could poſſeſſe here on earth, he accounted himſelfe but a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and a pilgrim in this world, and therefore was content, though his Tabernacle were pitched and removed in divers places: He was aſſured, that God in his good time, would provide an hiding place for him, either on the earth or in the grave, ſupporting himſelfe with <hi>Luthers</hi> holy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Calo, aut ſub Calo, that he ſhould either be under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of heaven, or in the poſſeſſion of heaven:</hi> His hope and beliefe in the watchfull providence of God was alwaies ſtrong, being rooted on that immovable foundation, the promiſes of God, of which he treaſured up ſuch ſtore in his memorie, that he could at any time look a danger, or death in the face. No doubt the contemplation of his Celeſtiall inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, thoſe new heavens, and new earth whereof he is now poſſeſſed, did raviſh his ſoul with an holy thirſt and longing after them: for the joy that was ſet before him, he could endure the croſſe, and deſpiſe the ſhame, and ſuffer the contradiction of ſinners, in high charitie commending them to the mercy of God, in that prayer, <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they doe.</hi> And laſtly, as if he had been of <hi>Beza's</hi> judgment, in the reading of this Text, that none but new creatures ſhould be admited into theſe new heavens, his heart was ſet upon righteouſneſſe, endeavouring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to keep a conſcience void of offence towards God and alſo towards man. Pietie, and learning, and modeſtie to meet in one man was hard and rare, and theſe met in him; his piety appeared in his care for Gods true worſhip, and in a diſcreet zeal for his houſe; he had a deſire to bring all men into that way, which in his conſcience he thought would lead to heaven. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> complained of ſome that did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Fit their faith to the times,</hi> and ſo make it as Saint <hi>Hilary</hi> cenſures it, <hi>Fides temporum, non Evangeliorum: a Faith moulded to the humor of the times, not according to the Doctrine of the Goſpell.</hi> He was none of thoſe his care was to pleaſe Chriſt, and to preach him; ſo that to the laſt gaſp' he was conſtant to the worſhip of God, and faithfull in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, I muſt profeſſe my ſelfe an incompetent cenſor of it; ſo farre as I was able to judge, he deſerved the name of <hi>Tri-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or,</hi> aſwell as <hi>Quintus Ennius,</hi> he underſtood thoſe three languages, <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew,</hi> in a good meaſure. In anſwer to <hi>Aarons Urim and Thummim,</hi> there were written and combined in his breaſt, <hi>Sci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntia,</hi> and <hi>Conſcientia, Learning,</hi> and <hi>integritie;</hi> he was able both by his learning and his life to confound the adverſaries of the truth of Chriſt: Theſe were the evidences of his righteouſneſſe towards God; and for his righteouſneſſe towards man, I am confident he might have gaſp'd out the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi>'s challenge,
<pb facs="tcp:168137:8"/>
               <hi>Whoſe Ox, or whoſe Aſſe have I taken?</hi> Yea, and added that of Saiu <hi>Paul, I have wronged no man, I have corrupted no man, I have defrauded no man, I have coveted no mans ſilver nor gold, nor apparell;</hi> he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with ſuch things as he had, remembring that promiſe of the Lord <hi>Let your converſation be without covetouſneſſe: for I will never leave you, nor for ſake you:</hi> It pleaſed the Lord to raiſe him friends and ſupplies even in his loweſt ſtate, whoſe charitie and compaſſion no doubt the Lord will both remember and reward, when they ſhall have moſt need of it. And in great teſtimony of his love and care over him, the Lord was his ſhield and buckler when both the Sword and the Sickneſſe raged round about him, and hath brought him to his grave in peace, in a good old age, where we are now to diſpoſſe the remains of him, till the conſummation of all things, when it ſhall pleaſe God to ſay, <hi>Come again ye children of men;</hi> and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the bones and duſt of deer and divided friends, and unite them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a bleſſed and glorious reſurrection.</p>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>The ſpeech at the grave.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WElbeloved friends we are met here to pay thoſe Chriſtian reſpects which we owe to the corps of our deceaſed Friend: the bodies of Chriſtians are the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, yea, they are the temples of the holy Ghost, and are therefore in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent manner to be interred and laid up in their long home the grave. This reverend brother of ours was a Preacher while he was living, and now, though dead, is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us his farewell ſermon, and his Text is</hi> Hodie mihi, cras tibi, <hi>this is my day of buriall, to morrow may be yours. The Lord in the death of every man performs the deſire of</hi> Dives <hi>in the parable: He ſends one from the dead to admoniſh us that all fleſh is graſſe, and the glory of man but as the flower of the graſſe, to remember us of that irreverſable ſtatute, and the penalty of it that it is appointed for all men once to die, and after death to come to judgment: 'Tis not the leaſt of the Lords mercies when he will convey the conſideration of ſerious matters to us in ſuch obvious and familiar notions, to remember us of our frailty and mortality, and make the graſſe of the field a looking-glaſſe wherein we may ſee our ſelves, and learn that as every g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe of the field proves, there is a God that made it: So every graſſe ſhewes what man is, and that there is a God that will turn him to deſtruction. Some Authors have told us that a ſwarm of bees fighting, are no way ſooner appeaſed then by throwing duſt amongſt them. Mankind is a ſwarm of Bees that buſie themſelves and buzze about the World, and are too often fighting and quarrelling, and an handfull of duſt taken into ſerious conſideration, would quiet them all, duſt is the embleme of mans originall, and his end, from whence he came and to what he must return: Duſt hath a medicinall quality to cure all the diſeaſes of the ſoul, eſpecially the tympany of pride: When hair is ſweet through pride or luſt the powder doth forget the duſt, we ſhould not ſo far diſparage the workmanſhip of God as to mend our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by art<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if we did conſider that ere long the duſt of the Grave would ſpoil our complexion: when Saint</hi> Auguſtine <hi>ſtood by the Temple of</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulius Caeſar, <hi>He cries out,</hi> Ubi nunc pulchritudo Caeſaris: <hi>what is become of</hi> Caeſars <hi>goodly perſon?
<pb facs="tcp:168137:9"/>
he ſpake it not by way of triumph as inſulting over the aſhes of that mighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, but to convey an instruction to all mankind, that were every Son of man as comely in perſon and as great as he, as high in armes, and as glorious in honour; yet his foundation is in the duſt ſaies holy</hi> Job, <hi>and must ſay to corruption,</hi> thou art my Father, <hi>and to the worm,</hi> thou art my Mother and my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſter. <hi>Though our bodies are as I ſaid the temples of the Holy Ghoſt; yet they will come to delapidation, and moulder into rubbidge and duſt; our bones will be ſcattered about the graves mouth like ſo many chiphs of a man that heweth wood, and our duſt may perchance be mingled with the duſt of the high wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, the materialls of our bodies which we ſo love and pamper now will be troden down, like the mire in the ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t if we would every one ſay, and ſay often to our ſelves in thoſe words of</hi> Job. The grave is ready for me, I am now in the beauty and flower of my youth, but know not how ſoon I may be cropt and wither; <hi>certainly ſuch meditations would make much for the advancement of piety in all our waies to remember our end, and ſo to live every day as if it we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e our laſt day. There paſſes a ſtory of</hi> Ben Syra <hi>a Iew, that when he was about twelve years old, he requeſted his Tutor to teach him the law of</hi> Moſes <hi>He anſwers,</hi> Child you are to young to learn or underſtand that Law: <hi>but the child replies,</hi> Sir, I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in down in the Church-yard among the graves, and I find that many are dead who were not ſo tall nor old as I, and I would be loath to die before I had learnt the law: <hi>this Iewes child may teach us Chriſtians a good leſſon, to take heed we do not die before we have learn'd the Law of God, and that danger we can no other way avoid but by meditating in the law day and night, and by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſtatutes of the Lord our guide and counſellours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am ſo charitable as to think that the confluence of friende and neighbours to this funerall hath no other deſign but to honour the memory of our reverend friend, and let me remember you of one point of honour ye may do him, which perchance you think not of, that is to become his converts, that at the laſt day when he ſhall ariſe, he may preſent himſelf and you before the Lord, and ſay,</hi> theſe are the children which I have begotten in my miniſtry, theſe are thoſe ſouls whom I have inſtructed and confirmed in the faith, theſe are they that in life and death have held forth the teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>this were truly to honour him, to make him ſhine like a ſtar of the first magnitude in the firmament of glory. And let this fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſolemnity give you occaſion when you depart hence to ſay:</hi> Mr. Wiborough did me much good while he lived, but more when he was dead, the ſermons that I heard from his mouth wrought much upon me, but his funerall ſermon more, when his breathleſſe corps preached to me, and bid me prepare for my diſſolution, when his duſt ſpake to me and bid me bury all thoſe ſinnes whereof he reproved me in the grave with him: <hi>ſo great are the reſpects and affection which this Gentleman did deſerve of us all, that I think you could be as well content to hear more of him as I to ſpeak, but I muſt conclude with that of</hi> Nazianzen, <hi>the Sea ſaith,</hi> he doth not need the rivers that yet run into it: <hi>ſo neither doth he need mine or any others praiſe, he hath fought the good fight of Faith, and finiſhed his courſe, and is now gone to receive his Crown of righteouſneſſe, as for his body we commend it to the grave, beſeeching the Lord to ſanctifie this and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpectacles of our mortality to us, and by them to teach us ſo to number our daies that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
